Guide to the Socialist Aldermen Papers TAM.056.007
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist Aldermen Papers
1917-1920
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York (N.Y.). Board of Aldermen
TAM.056.007
1 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
From 1917 to 1920, seven prominent socialists were elected on the Socialist Party ticket to serve on the New York City Board of Aldermen. The collection contains correspondence and subject files. Note: this collection has been microfilmed, and researchers must use the microfilm copy (R-7124, reel 11).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the microfilmed version; microfilm call number is Film R-7124, Reel 11.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Rand School Archives, 1962. The accession number associated with this collection is 1962.008.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
From 1917 to 1920, seven prominent socialists were elected to serve on the New York City Board of Aldermen. This delegation consisted of Abraham Beckerman, Alexander Braunstein, Adolph Held, Maurice S. Kalman, Algernon Lee, B. Charney Vladeck, and Barnet Wolff, with Charles Solomon serving as, executive secretary and Evans Clark serving as director. These aldermen sponsored research projects relating to various urban problems in New York City and drafted legislation concerning municipal ownership. During this period, the socialist aldermen worked diligently to implement many of the programs that had been advocated by the New York Socialist Party locals for a number of years. While most of these proposals were initially defeated, several socialist measures, including public ownership of mass transportation and administrative control over housing and the school lunch program, were finally adopted in the 1930s and 1940s.
Scope and Content Note
The Socialist Aldermen Papers, 1917-1920, consist of 19 subject files and 16 files of correspondence. The subject files are first arranged alphabetically according to the title of the file and then chronologically within each file. Each file has been assigned a microfilm frame number, with the subject files receiving numbers 1-19 and the correspondence receiving numbers 20-35. In a representative frame number (VII:2), the number 2 indicates that this is the 2nd frame, and the roman numeral VII indicates that the Socialist Alderman Papers are the 7th collection within the microfilm publication Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Organized into three series:
Missing Title
I. Subject Files
II. Correspondence
III. Fragile Originals
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist Assemblymen Papers. (Collection number: Tamiment 056.8)
Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956: A Guide to the Microfilm Edition (Sanford, N.C.: Microfilming Corp. of America, c1979), 181 p.
The Baruch Charney Vladeck Papers (Tamiment 037)
The Algernon Lee Papers (Tamiment 014)
Correspondence.; Municipal corporations.; Reports.; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; Socialism -- United States.; New York (N.Y.); Wolff, Barnet; Socialist Party (U.S.); Clark, Evans.; Kalman, Maurice S; Solomon, Charles; Lee, Algernon; Held, Adolph, 1885-1969.; Vladeck, B. (Baruch), 1886-1938; Beckerman, Abraham; Braunstein, Alexander
- Series I. Subject Files
  - Aldermanic Investigations, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:1
  - Board of Education, Nurseries, May 2, 1913-May 3, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:2
  - Bridges, Dec 31, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:3
  - City Employees: Wages, Benefits, Working Conditions, Feb 19, 1918-May 31, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:4
  - Coal Distribution, Jan 7, 1918-May 14, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:5
  - Finances, Jan 4, 1917-Apr 2, 1905, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:6
  - Franchises, Nov 15, 1910-Mar 9, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:7
  - Health, May 7, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:8
  - Housing, Parks, Jul 3, 1917-Apr 18, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:9
  - Ice Trade, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:10
  - Labor League, Jan 25, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:11
  - Memorandum, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:12
  - Minutes of Meetings of Socialist Aldermanic Delegation, Dec 6, 1917-Jun 10, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:13
  - Municipal Trading, Feb 28, 1917-Apr 9, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:14
  - Roth, Louis, "Public Utilities in New York City", 1917 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:15
  - Resolutions, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:16
  - School Lunches, Jan 17, 1917-May 9, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:17
  - Subways and Public Ownership, Mar 19, 1913-Nov 10, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:18
  - Miscellaneous, Feb 8, 1918-Oct 16, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:19
- Series II. Correspondence
  - A, Sep 3, 1918-Apr 21, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:20
  - B, Oct 30, 1918-Feb 21, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:21
  - C, Oct 22, 1918-Feb 3, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:22
  - D, Oct 31, 1918-Jan 24, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:23
  - E-F, Oct 31, 1918-Jan 21, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:24
  - G, Oct 16, 1918-Apr 17, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:25
  - H, Oct 14, 1918-Oct 16, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:26
  - K-L, Oct 7, 1918-Mar 1, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:27
  - M, Oct 10, 1918-Feb 15, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:28
  - N-O, Dec 5, 1918-Jun 10, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:29
  - P-Q, Dec 2, 1918-Jun 10, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:30
  - R, Oct 24, 1918-Feb 28, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:31
  - S, Aug 13, 1918-Feb 26, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:32
  - T-V, Oct 25, 1918-Mar 4, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:33
  - W, Sep 27, 1918-Apr 15, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:34
  - Z, Nov 1, 1918-Dec 27, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Film R-7124, Reel 11: Frame VII:35
- Series III. Fragile Originals
  - Fragile Originals Box 1, Folder 1 through Box 1, Folder 20 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fragile Originals Box 2, Folder 1 through Box 2, Folder 6 (Box 3, Folder 2)